we're continuing to talk about
representations of Lee groups and Lee
algebras in this video we're going to
discuss the tensor product of
representations in physics courses the
tensor product of representations gives
us instructions for addition of angular
momentum in systems of multiple
particles in previous videos I mentioned
how all fundamental particles have a
property called spin which is either an
integer or a half integer spin zero
particles transform like scalers spin 1
half particles transform like Spinners
spin one particles transform like
vectors and there are higher spin
particles as well an important fact here
is that all these objects can be
constructed from tensor products of
different numbers of spinners so in a
certain sense Spinners are the most
basic fundamental object that can be
used to build all other particle like
objects
so in this video we're going to look at
systems of multiple spin one half
particles or Spinners and see how they
combine together into multi-particle
systems using the tensor
product as an example a pair of spin 1/2
electrons can bind together in a solid
at low temperatures into Cooper pairs or
BCS Pairs and behave more like a spin
one vector particle or a spin zero
scalar particle
this is a key fact underlying the
phenomenon of
superconductivity because spin one and
spin zero particles are bons and bosons
can all occupy the same state unlike
half integer spin firmians which must
obey Po's exclusion
principle in the language of
representation Theory we would say that
the tensor product of two irreducible
spin 1/ half representations becomes the
direct sum of a spin one EP and a spin
zero a rephrased using Dimensions the
tensor product of a pair of 2x two ARS
equals the direct sum of the 3X3 EP and
the 1x1
EP this will lead us to the kch Gordon
coefficients which tell us how to take
Spinners in the coupled basis and build
states in the total angular momentum
basis also in this video I will often
refer to all cats as States or or
vectors because they live in Vector
spaces but when I talk about the vector
representation of su2 I'm specifically
talking about the spin one
representation of su2 which transforms
3D
vectors so before we discuss tensor
product representations let's review the
direct sum and the tensor product the
basic summary is that the direct sum
will add dimensions of two Vector spaces
and the tensor product will multiply the
dimensions of two Vector
spaces if we have a vector v in 3D space
and a vector W in 2D space we can write
both of them as columns the direct sum
of V and W involves stacking the columns
on top of each other into a 5D Vector
this Vector lives in a new
five-dimensional space with five basis
vectors which is just the 3D basis and
the 2D basis put
together if there's a 3X3 linear map L
that acts on V and a 2x2 linear map K
that acts on W then the direct sum of L
and K is a 5x5 block diagonal matrix
like
this if we multiply this onto the direct
sum of V and W the L part of the Matrix
acts on V and the K part of the Matrix
acts on
W more abstractly if we see the direct
sum of L and K act on the direct sum of
V and W we can just pass V to L and pass
W to K to get our
result the tensor product on the other
hand is a bit harder to understand the
tensor product of a vector v in 3D space
and a vector W in 2D space is a
six-dimensional vector the new basis in
six-dimensional space uses all possible
pairs of basis vectors from from the 3D
space and the 2D
space one way to think about the tensor
product of V and W is as the column row
outer product of V and W transpose which
gives us six
components in this case we're viewing v
as a vector and viewing W transpose as a
dual Vector to see how this six
component object transforms we can
transform V using the 3X3 L Matrix from
the left and transform W transpose using
the 2x two k transpose Matrix from the
right so we get a double-sided
transformation like this if we're
dealing with complex Vector spaces we
use the Herm Mission conjugate operation
instead of the transpose
operation however it's also good to know
how to take the tensor product of two
column
vectors the tensor product of arrays is
also called the chroniker product and it
works as follows the tensor product of
the column V and the column W involves
taking each component of v and
multiplying it by an entire copy of the
two component column W the result is a
six component column with the components
of V and W mixed
together similarly for the tensor
product of matrices L and K we can
multiply each component of L in the 3X3
matrix by an entire copy of the 2x2
Matrix K the result is a 6x6 Matrix that
can operate on our six component column
the resulting component multiplications
end up being the same as the column row
version we showed
earlier more abstractly if we see the
tensor product of L and K act on the
tensor product of V and W we can pass V
to L and pass W to K to get our
result an important difference between
the direct sum and the tensor product is
how scalar multiplication works when we
scale the direct sum of vectors V and W
we're scaling the entire column so both
V and W get Scaled by the
scaler so when we scale a direct sum
both elements in the sum get the scaling
coefficient however since the tensor
product of vectors V and W is done as a
kind of array multiplication we scale
the mixture of V and W so when we scale
this tensor product we can choose to
either scale V or scale W but we don't
scale
both also the tensor product obeys the
distributive property over vector
addition in both
directions when we deal with systems of
multiple particles the laws of quantum
mechanics say that we must combine the
particle States together using the
tensor product for example example if we
have a system of two spin 1/2 particles
each with two states then the tensor
product space has a basis given by all
possible pairs of particle
States we can rotate these State pairs
using the tensor product of a pair of
su2
matrices for a system of three spin 1
half particles the tensor product space
has a basis given by all possible
triples of particle States we and then
rotate them using the tensor product of
a triple of su2
matrices to save space in Quant
mechanics we often omit the tensor
product symbol and write all the
particle States in a single K like
this so whenever we have matrices from a
Le group like su2 we know the rule for
how the tensor product of Le group
matrices will act on the tensor product
of States but what about the matrices in
a lead group groups Lee algebra for
example how would the latter operators
and igen value operator work on tensor
product
States recall given a Lee group with the
identity element as one of its points
the group's Lee algebra is like a
tangent space at the identity of the
group a Lee algebra element is like a
tangent Vector in this tangent
space when a Lee algebra element is
exponentiated along with a parameter it
will generate a continuous path of group
members in the Le group when the
parameter is zero we get the identity
element which is where the Lee algebra
tangent space meets the Lee
group to go from the Le group Matrix
back to the generator in the Lee algebra
we take the derivative of the group
element and then set the parameter to
zero this derivative brings the Lee
algebra generator down in front by Chain
Rule and setting the parameter to Zer
makes the exponential go to the identity
leaving us with just the
generator let's say that we have a Le
group path a of t with generator small a
and another path B of t with generator
small B we can get these generators by
taking the derivative and then setting
the parameter T to
zero if we have the tensor product of a
of T and B of T we can find this
element's generator the usual way
by taking the derivative and setting the
parameter T to
zero to take the derivative we use
product rule over the tensor product and
get a sum of two terms then we set the
parameter T to Zero by definition A of0
and B of0 both equal the identity
element since the parameter being zero
gives the identity
transformation and setting T equals z
for the derivatives is just the
definition of the original generators
small a and small
B so we see the tensor product group
element is generated by small a tensor
the identity plus the identity tensor
small B so we can obtain this Le group
member a of T tensor B of T by
exponentiating this Lee algebra
generator times a parameter
T so let's say we have two Le group
representations Row one and row two that
give us Matrix representation ations for
elements of a group G we can define a
new group representation Row one tensor
Row Two of a group element just by
taking the element's first
representation Matrix and second
representation Matrix and taking the
tensor product of the
matrices therefore the tensor product of
a 3X3 representation and a 2x2
representation would give us a 6x6
representation but what about the
corresponding Lee algebra
representation if we have two
representations Pi 1 and Pi 2 of a Lee
algebra small G then the tensor product
representation of an algebra element is
given by the first representation Matrix
tensored with the identity plus the
identity tensored with the second
representation
Matrix if small L generates L of t a 3X3
Matrix and small K generates K of t a
2x2 matrix then L of T tensor K of T
will be generated by small L tensor the
2x2 identity plus the 3X3 identity
tensor small K note that after we carry
out the tensor product both matrices in
the sum will be
6x6 so we get a sum of two 6x6
matrices so these definitions work for
any pair of Le group representations and
their Lee
algebras but let's get back to the
specific case of the su2 Le group and
the su2 Lee algebra let's see what
happens when we apply these rules to the
case of a pair of spin 1/2 su2
representations recall the su2 Lee
algebra is defined using these
commutation relations of three
generators and the raising and lowering
operators and igen value operator are
defined like this for the spin 1/2
representation of su2 the generators are
given by 2x two
matrices these generators act on a
two-dimensional Vector space with two
basis
elements it's common to label these
basis elements as plus2 and minus one2
which are their igen values under the gz
operator however for Simplicity I'm
going to label them with an up arrow and
a down arrow respectively because they
denote the spin up and and spin down
states of a
particle if we have a pair of su2 Lee
algebras each represented with the spin
1/2 representation and we take their
tensor product the dimensions will
multiply into a four-dimensional space
the basis States would then be up tensor
up up tensor down down tensor up and
down tensor down again to save space
I'll often omit the tensor product
symbol and write the arrows in the same
Vector but I'll be using both of these
notations in this
video we can take the generators in the
S2 Lee algebra and extend them to the
space su2 tensor
su2 we just take the operator tensor the
identity plus the identity tensor the
operator the IG value and Ladder
operators which live in the complexified
version of these Lee algebras can be
extended in the same way
so the notation here can get a little
confusing but the igen value operator
that lives in the su2 tensor product
space is made up of igen value operators
from the individual su2
spaces I'm going to use the same symbol
for both of these cases but it should be
clear from Context what I mean if an
operator acts on an individual State
it's an individual su2 operator if an
operator Act on a tensor product State
it's the tensor product su2
operator so we can use these tensor
product ladder operators to travel up
and down the ladder of states in the
tensor product space and use the tensor
product igen value operator to get the
igen values of the tensor product
States let's start by getting the igen
values for these four states under the
gz operator starting with the UP UP
State
we can write out the operator in the
tensor product representation using the
definition we just learned for Le
algebras and we can write the state
using the tensor product
notation here we have a sum of two
linear Maps so we just distribute the
input to each linear map in the
sum next we pass the tensor product
inputs to the tensor product of The
Operators the first state goes to the
first operator and the second State goes
to the second
operator the gzs acting on the up States
will return an IG value of plus2 and the
identity operators just leave the states
as they are using the rules of the
tensor product we can pull the one
halfes out in front and then add the
states together we find that the IG
value of the UP UP State is
one now notice what happened here is
that the first gz operator acted on the
first state and the second gz operator
acted on the second state and then we
just added the two I values together to
get one so if we have a state with I
value M1 and another state with I value
M2 and we take their tensor product in
the tensor product States their combined
igen value is just M1 + M2 this is
because the first state gets a gz and
the second state also gets a gz so the
Aon values are just summ
together so let's use this trick to
quickly get the igen values of our
tensor product States we already know
that the IG value of the UP UP State
gives 1 12 + 12 = 1 the up down state
will have an IG value of a half - a half
equal 0 the down up state will have an I
value of minus a half plus a half equal
Z and the down down state will have an I
value of -2 -2 =
min-1 if this isn't obvious I'd
encourage you to pause the video and try
the calculations manually
yourself now let's try using the raising
and lowering operators on these states
recall the raising operator sends the
down state to the UP State and sends the
UP State to zero the lowering operator
sends the UP State to the down state and
sends the down state to zero basically
we can't raise a state of above the
highest IG value and we can't lower a
state below the lowest IG value and
recall in this case the igon values are
sometimes called
weights in our tensor product space the
up up state has the highest I value so
it would make sense that the raising
operator would send it to zero let's
confirm
that we can write the operator and state
out fully with tensor products then we
can pass the input state to the two
linear Maps then pass the first states
to the first operators and the second
states to the second
operators now here when the raising
operators act on the up States they go
to zero so both tensor products go to
zero and we get zero as a result so the
UP UP State is indeed the highest weight
State as
expected now we can use the lowering
operators to lower this state down the
lad
and get a basis of En States under
gz if we apply the lowering operator to
the UP UP State we get a sum of two
terms where the first term has the first
state lowered to down and the second
term has the second state lowered to
down so we end up with the state down up
plus up down if we apply the igen value
operator to this state we get zero so we
have indeed lowered the igen value by
one
if we now apply the lowering operator
again we have two inputs sent to a sum
of linear Maps so expanding we get four
terms lowering on the down States gives
zero and lowering on the up States gives
down States so we end up with the down
down state with a coefficient of two in
front the ion value operator gives an
ion value of minus one so again we
lowered the ion value by one
now one thing to remember is that the
raising and lowering operators give
result states that are multiplied by
coefficients which I called Alpha and
beta in the previous video These
coefficients depend on the spin
representation number J and the state IG
value M since the IG values of these
states are + one 0 and minus1 this is a
spin one
representation and the beta code
coefficients are the square root of
two if we take the states obtained from
the lowering operator and take these
coefficients into account we get this
set of three states for our spin one
representation these states are actually
normalized to one so they're easier to
work
with now a problem here is that if we
try to lower the down down state we get
zero so this is the lowest igen value
state
this is a bit weird because the tensor
product space is
four-dimensional but the space given to
us by the latter operators is only
three-dimensional so what happened to
the extra Dimension it turns out the
answer to this mystery is that the space
actually has two highest weight vectors
the one we missed is down up minus up
down if we apply the raising operator to
it we get up up minus up up which is
zero
so this is indeed a highest weight State
and if we lower the state we get down
down minus down down which is zero so
this is also a lowest weight State the
state also has an I value of
zero so what's going on here is that
this tensor product space actually has
two su2 representations living inside it
we have a 3D representation with State
IG values + one 0 and minus1
this is a spin one
representation these are sometimes
called triplet States we also have a one
dimensional representation whose state
has I value zero this is a spin zero
representation this is sometimes called
the singlet
state so the tensor product of a pair of
2D representations of su2 decomposes
into the direct sum of a 3D
representation of su2 and a 1D
representation of
su2 we often write this fact as 2 tensor
2 = 3 sum
1 and remember we can get the spin
number J of a representation by taking
the dimension n of the representation
subtracting one and dividing by two so
we can also write this equation using
spin numbers instead so the tensor
product of a pair of spin 1/2
representations equals the direct sum of
a spin one represent ation and a spin
zero
representation however I prefer the
first Formula with the dimensions
because if we interpret this as an
elementary school math equation the
numbers actually work
out it's also common to write these IR
basis vectors using the JM notation
where J is the spin number and M is the
igen value the triplet States belong to
a spin one representation so they all
have J values of one
and their igen values M are + one 0 and
minus1 the singlet State belongs to a
spin 0 representation so J equals 0 its
I value m is also equal to
[Music]
zero this procedure of taking the tensor
product of two representations is what
physicists call addition of angular
momentum for two particles the J value
gives the total angular momentum for a
system of particles
and the igen value M indicates the
component of angular momentum along the
Z
AIS in physics these are both multiplied
by H
bar we usually use an operator
associated with the square of the total
angular momentum in quantum mechanics
this operator is also called the Casmir
Operator by mathematicians and in my
videos I've been denoting it as g^
s this operator commutes with all of the
elements in the Lee algebra and when it
acts on the state it returns J * J + 1
where J is the spin number for the
representation that state belongs
to now for tensor product
representations you might be tempted to
try and write g^ SED using the same
formula we used for the other operators
but we cannot actually do this the
reason for this is that the Kazmir
operator doesn't actually live inside
the Le
algebra because it is defined using the
squares of operators and Lee algebras
don't understand what squaring operators
means Lee algebras only understand the
Lee
bracket to get the correct definition of
the Kazmir operator in tensor product
spaces we need to take our original
formula for the Kazmir operator from the
last video and replace each operator
with the tensor product version we get
the tensor product style formula we're
used to with Le algebras plus some extra
parts we can label our first particle
with J1 and M1 and label our second
particle with J2 and M2 then we can
combine them with the tensor product and
see what we get when we apply the Kazmir
operator to
it if we try applying our Kazmir
operator to the UP UP State and Sub in
all the related values for the first and
second particles we get a result of two
this is exactly the result we expect for
a total angular momentum of capital J
equaling
1 we get the same J equals 1 result for
all of the triplet States and for the
singlet State the Kazmir operator gives
us a j value of
zero so this really is the direct sum of
a spin one and spin zero representation
as
expected so in our tensor product space
we've discovered two different bases we
have the standard tensor product basis
also called the coupled basis but we
also have the basis where we've
decomposed the space into a spin one a
and a spin zero a I'll call this the a
basis physicists will usually call it
the total angular momentum
basis the first number here capital J is
the spin value of the representation and
the second number capital M is the igen
value of a state under the gz
operator so the EP basis states can all
be written out as linear combinations of
the tensor product basis States if we
include the terms with zero coefficients
we get 16 coefficients in
total we can arrange all of these
coefficients into a matrix with the
tensor product States arranged on the
side and the IR basis States arranged up
top
a given column tells us which
coefficients are needed to build up that
column's EP basis
State now I'm going to rewrite the up
States using the plus 1/2 I value and
rewrite the down States using the minus
one2 I value I'm also going to rewrite
the EP basis States so that the spin
value J is on top and the I value m is
on the
bottom next I'm going to remove the zero
value in The Matrix and position the
basis vectors like
this this is called the kch Gordon table
for the spin 1/2 tensor spin 1/2
representation of
su2 the way this table works is to build
a given a basis Vector on top you just
read the column below it for the
coefficients you need to build it with
the tensor product basis States shown on
the left so for example to build the Jal
1 m 0 State we need 1/ the < TK of 2 *
the +2 -2 State plus 1/ the < TK of 2 *
the -2 + 1/2 State you might find this
table a little easier to read when it's
in the full 4x4 Matrix form but with a
little practice you should be able to
get used to reading it like
this it's also common to remove the
square roots from the coefficients to
save space so you'll need to remember to
add the square roots back in yourself if
the table is written like
this we can also interpret these
coefficients as being the inner product
of the states in the two
bases these inner product coefficients
end up being the same as the
coefficients in the linear combinations
because all the states are normalized
and
orthogonal I've included a link in the
description to a page with this and
other KP Gordon
tables so at this point we basically
know everything we need to know about
the spin 1/2 tensor spin 1/2
representation we know it decomposes
into a direct sum of a spin one EP and a
spin zero EP and we know the
coefficients for changing to the ere rep
basis now let's try looking at the
tensor product of three spin 1/2 su2 ARS
which has eight basis
States we get operators in the lead
algebra exactly as we did before if we
have League group members a of t b of T
and C of t with generators small a small
B small C we can get the generator of a
of T tensor B of T tensor C of T by
taking the derivative and setting the
parameter to zero product rule gives us
a sum of three terms this time and
setting T equals z the three derivative
terms each give a generator and the
other terms just give identity
so we have a sum of three terms each
containing one Lee algebra generator in
one of the three
positions this immediately gives us
definitions for the igen value and
Ladder
operators as before the ion value
operator acting on a tensor product
State simply gives the ion values of
each state in the tensor product and
sums them
together so the I value of the up up up
state is a half plus a half plus plus a
half equal
3es this is a highest weight State and
we can use the lowering operator to
build the rest of the bases for a spin
three Hales
ER we can also find two other highest
weight States and we find they each give
us a spin 1/2 a
rep if we take the beta coefficients
from the lowering operator into account
we get these normalized states
here so the tensor product of three spin
1/2 EPS decomposes into the direct sum
of a spin three Hales EP a spin 1/2 and
another spin
1/2 in other words the tensor product of
three
2x2s decomposes into the direct sum of a
4x4 EP and a pair of
2x2s we can see all the a basis vectors
here for the spin 3 haves a we get four
basis vectors
and for each of the spin 1/2s we get two
basis
vectors we can go through a similar
process for the tensor product of four
spin 1/2 EPS all of the four tensor
operators work as you'd
expect I'm not going to go through the
details but this representation
decomposes into the direct sum of eps
with spins 2 1 0 1 1 and 0er in terms of
the dimensions the ears in the direct
sum have Dimensions 5 3 1 3 3 and
1 I'm showing the first three ears here
and the second three IRS
here now there's a trick from Mark
Thompson's modern particle physics book
that helps us get these EP
decompositions more easily we can
illustrate the two-dimensional su2 EP as
two states represented as two nodes
connected by a line segment M the lad
operators move us between the two nodes
this is called a weight
diagram if we have two of these EPs and
we take their tensor product we can
illustrate the result by taking the
first diagram and placing a copy of the
second diagram centered on each of the
two
nodes we get a weight diagram with three
nodes this shows that the result
contains a 3D EP which are the triplet
States however since the middle location
here contains two overlapping nodes one
of them pops out and becomes a 1D ere
the singlet
State this illustrates the IR formula we
saw earlier where the tensor product of
a pair of 2D IRS equals the direct sum
of a 3D EP and a 1D
EP we can continue this pattern for the
tensor product of three 2D EPS we know
the first two weight diagrams in the
product result in a sum of a 3D ere and
a 1D
ere now we can distribute the product
over the sum as if this were an algebra
equation to calculate these products we
can again use the trick of taking the
first diagram in the product and placing
a copy of the second diagram in the
product over each
node the first term in the sum gives us
a 4D EP however since there are two node
overlaps a 2d EP also pops out and the
second term gives us a 2d
ER in this way we see the product of
three 2D ARS gives us the sum of a 4D ER
and a pair of 2D ER reps as we saw
before we can keep going with the tensor
product of four 2D EPS we know the first
three become four Su two Su two then we
distribute to get the sum of three
products then we use the trick of taking
the first diagram and placing copies of
the second diagram over its nodes in
this way we see the tensor product of
four 2D EPS gives us the sum of IRS with
Dimensions 533 131 as we saw
earlier now if we look at all the tensor
product representations so far the
largest EP in each one increases by half
an integer spin each time in other words
the largest IR increases by one
dimension each time
let's take a closer look at these
largest EPS that result from the tensor
products the tensor product of two
spinners gives us a largest EP of a spin
one particle or vector which is a rank
one tensor the tensor product of three
Spinners gives us the largest EP of a
spin three Hales
particle the tensor product of four
Spinners gives us a largest ER of a spin
two particle or Rank 2 tensor and so on
in this way the tensor product of an
even number of spinners can be thought
of as the fundamental building block for
all tensor ranks and the tensor product
of an odd number of spinners gives us a
kind of tensor that can be thought of as
having a half integer rank these are
sometimes called spinner
tensors the largest IRS inside the
tensor product spaces all have the
property of being totally symmetric this
means that if you swap any to spin
values in the basis States the overall
state is
unchanged for example in this spin 3
haves ER if I exchange the position of
the first and second spin States in all
the basis States the overall basis
states are
unchanged so all the tensors and spin
tensors associated with su2 in three
dimensions of space can all be
constructed as totally symmetric states
of some number of spinners multiplied
together with the tensor product
now so far in this video we've been
focusing on the tensor product of spin
1/2 su2
representations but we can also take the
tensor products of representations of
other sizes as well for example the
tensor product of a spin 1/2 a and a
spin three Hales a or the tensor product
of a spin one and a spin one a in each
case we can change the basis from the
tensor product basis to the IR basis
which is where the space is decomposed
into a direct sum of smaller
ears the change of basis equations for
doing this are given by sets of larger
KP Gordon tables which I've Linked In
the
description to use the tables you start
by identifying the two representations
you're tensoring together this tells you
which table to use in this example we'll
look at spin one tensored with spin one
along the top you'll see the various
basis vectors in the EP basis labeled
with their spin number J followed by
their igen value M for example here we
have a decomposition into a spin 2 itre
with five basis States a spin one EP
with three basis States and a spin zero
EP with one basis
State along the sides you can see pairs
of igen values M1 and M2 for the two
vectors being used in the tensor
product to get the coefficients for a
given IR Vector we just read the column
for the coefficients and looked to the
left for the basis states that they are
matched with don't forget that you need
to include the square root signs over
these coefficients because they have
been left out to save space the minus
signs always belong on the outside of
the square root signs I've linked to
some other videos in the description if
you want more details on calculating and
reading these
tables the trick with drawing weight
diagrams also works here to compute the
product of a pair of 3D IRS we take the
first diagram and place a copy of the
second diagram centered on each node we
see we get a 5D erra three of the nodes
have two overlaps so a 3D EP pops out
also the middle node has three overlaps
so the final one pops out as a 1D
rep as expected the tensor product of a
pair of 3D reps decomposes into five
some three some
one so this concludes the explanation of
tensor product representations of su2 I
still need to talk about how the tensor
product is involved with representations
of SL2 C for space time however I've
realized that topic is so big that it
requires its own video so that will be
coming next